THE GRYB

A. E. Van Vogt

'The Gryb' was originally published as 'Repetition' in Astounding Science-Fiction Magazine, April 1940. Copyright 1940 by Street and Smith Publications, Inc. (now Conde Nast Publications, Inc.): copyright renewed 1968 by A. E. van Vogt.

His eyes ached! He kept blinking them as he flew, striving to keep in sight the glitter of hurtling metal that was the power-driven spacesuit of his guide.

The man was desperately hard to see against the blazing brilliance of the remote disk of sun - incredibly small and gemlike sun, rising higher and higher from the fantastic horizon of Europa. It was almost, Thomas told himself, as if the guide was deliberately holding himself into the glare of the morning sun to distract his - Thomas's - wearying mind and dull his strength.

More than a mile below, a scatter of forest spread unevenly over a grim, forbidding land. Pock-marked rock, tortured gravel, and occasionally a sparse, reluctant growth of Jupiter grass that shone as brown and uninviting as the bare straggle of forest - and was gone into distance as they sped far above, two shining things of metal, darting along with the speed of shooting stars.

Several times Thomas saw herds of the tall, dapple-grey grass eaters below; and once, far to the left, he caught the sheeny glint of a scale-armoured, blood-sucker gryb.

It was hard to see his speedometer, built into the transparent headpiece of his flying space armour - hard because he had on a second headpiece underneath, attached to his electrically heated clothes; and the light from the sun split dazzlingly through the two barriers. But now that his suspicions were aroused, he strained his eyes against that glare until they watered and blurred. What he saw tightened his heavy jaw into a thin, hard line. He snapped into his communicators, his voice as cold and hard as his thoughts: 'Hey, you ahead there - what's your name? Barkett, Birkett - '

'Bartlett, sir!' a young man's voice sounded in his communicators; and it seemed to the older man's alert hearing that the accent on the 'sir' held the faintest suggestion of a sneer, and a definite hostility. 'Ray Bartlett! What is it, sir?'

'You told me this trip would be five hundred and twenty-one miles or - '

'Or thereabouts!' The reply was swift, but the sneer was stronger, the hostility more apparent, more intentional.

Thomas's eyes narrowed to steely grey slits. 'You said five hundred and twenty-one miles. The figure is odd enough to be presumed exact, and there is no possibility that you would not know the exact distance from the Five Cities to the platinum mines. We have now travelled five hundred and twenty-nine miles - more every minute - since leaving the Five Cities a little over an hour ago, and - '

'So we have!' interrupted the young man with unmistakable insolence. 'Now isn't that too bad, Mr Famous Statesman Explorer Thomas.'

Thomas was silent, examining the situation for its potential menace. His first indignant impulse was to pursue the unexpected arrogance of the other, but his brain, suddenly crystal-clear, throttled the desire and leaped ahead in a blaze of speculation.

There was murder intent here. His mind ticked coldly, with a sense of something repeated; for the threat of death he had faced before, during those bold, tremendous years when he had roamed the farthest planets. It was icily comforting to know that this was but a repetition of what he had previously experienced - comforting to remember that he had conquered in the past. In murder, as in everything else, experience counted.

Thomas began to decelerate against the fury of built-up velocity. It would take time - but perhaps there still was time, though the other's attitude suggested the crisis was dangerously near. There was no more he could do till he had slowed considerably. Thomas quieted his leaping pulses and said gently:

'Tell me, is the whole community in on this murder? Or is it a scheme of your own?'

'There's no harm in telling you now!' Bartlett retorted. 'We knew in advance that your visit here was a farce. Ostensibly you came to find out for the Earth government if this moon of Jupiter was worth fighting about; actually, the government had decided in advance that they weren't going to fight, and you, with your terrific reputation, were to come here and put the thing over, pretending to be fair, but - '

His voice broke in a flare of hater 'You sneaking coward! What about the folks who've been trying to make a living here, slaving, hoping, dreaming, planning, creating for the future? And for what! So that a bunch of cynical politicians can sell us down the river to a dirty, arrogant gang of Martians.'

Thomas laughed, a hard, humourless but understanding laugh that hid the slow caution with which he slanted towards the ground. The strain of the curving dive racked his body, tore at his lungs, but he held to it grimly.

He was alone in the sky now] the shining spacesuit of the guide had vanished into the dim distance. Evidently the man had not turned his head or noticed the deviation on his finder. Anxious for the discovery to be as long delayed as possible, Thomas said:

'So that's it. I see that I am now confronted with the emotional immaturities of a bunch of child minds. I wonder if the human race will ever grow up. Don't you know that at one time the world was divided into warring nations, and before that into fiercely patriotic States; and before that human beings owed their loyalties to towns ? Will we always have such fools to contend with? Well-meaning fools, who understand nothing of political, social or vital economy, and are perpetually victims of their own undisciplined desires and emotional incoherencies.'

'Yah!' Ray Bartlett snarled. 'That kind of talk may go over big in the drawing-rooms of London and New York, but it's plain rot to the men and women who stand to lose their homes. You're going to die because we're not letting you get back with any lying story about Europa. We're going to fake up some notes in your handwriting - we've got a handwriting expert - and then we'll give the notes to the newspapers; and let the government try to back out after that. With you dead - '

Thomas asked grimly: 'And how are you going to kill me ?'

'In about ten seconds,' the young man began tautly, 'your engine - ' He broke off. 'Hah, you're not behind me any more. So you're trying to land. Well, it won't do you any good, damn your soul! I'll be right back that way - '

Thomas was only fifty feet from the bleak rock when there was a sudden grinding in the hitherto silent mechanism of his atomic motor. The deadly swiftness of what happened then left no time for more than instinctive action. He felt a pain against his legs, a sharp, tearing pain, a dizzy, burning sensation that staggered his reason - and then he had struck the ground - and with a wild, automatic motion jerked off the power that was being so horribly short-circuited, that was burning him alive. Darkness closed over his brain like an engulfing blanket -

The blurred world of rock swaying and swirling about him -that was Thomas's awakening! He forced himself to consciousness and realized after a moment of mental blankness that he was no longer in his spacesuit. And, when he opened his eyes he could see without a sense of dazzle, now that he had only the one helmet - the one attached to his electrically heated clothes. He grew aware of something - an edge of rock - pressing painfully into his back. Dizzily, but with sane eyes, he looked up at a lean-faced young man, who was kneeling beside him.

The young man - Ray Bartlett - returned his gaze with unsmiling hostility, and said curtly:

'You're lucky to be alive. Obviously you shut off the motor just in time. It was being shorted by lead grit, and burned your legs a little. I've put some salve on, so you won't feel any pain; and you'll be able to walk.'

He stopped and climbed to his feet. Thomas shook his head to clear away the black spots, and then gazed up at the other questioningly, but he said nothing. The young man seemed to realize what was in his mind.

'I didn't think I'd be squeamish with so much at stake,' he confessed almost roughly, 'but 1 am. I came back to kill you, but I wouldn't even kill a dog without giving him a chance. Well, you've got your chance, if it's worth anything.'

Thomas sat up, his eyes narrowed on the young man's face inside the other's helmet. Ray Bartlett was a handsome young fellow with a pleasing countenance that ordinarily must have been frank and open. It was an honest face, twisted now with resentment and a sort of dogged determination.

Frowning with thought, Thomas looked around; and his eyes, trained for detail, saw a lack in the picture.

'Where's your spacesuit!'

Ray Bartlett nodded his head skyward. His voice held no quality of friendliness as he said: 'If your eyes are good, you'll see a dark spot, almost invisible now,, to the right of the sun., I chained your suit to mine, then gave mine power. They'll be falling into Jupiter about three hundred hours from now.'

Thomas pondered that matter-of-factly. 'You'll pardon me if I don't quite believe that you've decided to stay and die with me. I know that men will die for what they believe to be right. But I can't quite follow the logic of why you should die. No doubt you have made arrangements to be rescued.'

Ray Bartlett flushed, his face growing dark with the turgid wave of angry colour. 'There'll be no rescue,' he growled from his throat. 'I didn't like what you said about undisciplined desires and emotional immaturities. I know what you meant - that we of the Five Cities were thinking selfishly of ourselves, blind to the general welfare. I'm going to prove to you that, in this matter, no individual in our community thinks of himself. I'm going to die here with you because, naturally, we'll never reach the Five Cities on foot, and as for the platinum mines, they're even farther away.'

'Pure bravado!' Thomas said. 'In the first place your staying with me proves nothing but that you're a fool; in the second, I am incapable of admiring such an action. However, I'm glad you're here with me, and I appreciate the salve on these burns.'

Thomas climbed gingerly to his feet, testing his legs, first the right, then the left, and felt a little sickening surge of dizziness that he fought back with an effort. 'Hm-m-m,' he commented aloud in the same matter-of-fact manner as before. 'No pain, but weak. That salve ought to have healed the burns by dark.'

'You take it very calmly,' said Ray Bartlett acridly.

Thomas nodded his powefully built head. 'I'm always glad to realize I'm alive; and I feel that I can convince you that the course being pursued by the government of which I am a minister is the only sane one.'

The young man laughed harshly. 'Fat chance. Besides, it doesn't matter. You don't seem to realize our predicament. We're at least twelve days from civilization - that's figuring sixty miles a day, which is hardly possible. Tonight, the temperature will fall to a hundred below freezing, at least, though it varies down to as low as a hundred and seventy-five below, depending on the shifting of Europa's core, which is very hot, you know, and very close to the surface at times. That's why human beings - and other life - can exist on this moon at all. The core is jockeyed around by the Sun and Jupiter, with the Sun dominating, so that it's always fairly warm in the daytime and why, also, when the pull is on the other side of the planet, it's so devilish cold at night, I'm explaining this to you, so you'll have an idea of what it's all about.'

'Go on,' Thomas replied without comment.

'Well, if the cold doesn't kill us, we're bound to run into at least one bloodsucker gryb every few days. They can smell human blood at an astounding distance; and blood for some chemical reason drives them mad with desire. Once they corner a human being it's all up. They tear down the largest trees, or dig into caves through solid rock. The only protection is an atomic gun, and ours went up with our suits. We've only got my hunting knife. Besides all that, our only possible food is the giant grass eater, which runs like a deer at the first sight of anything living, and which, besides, could kill a dozen unarmed men if it was cornered. You'll be surprised how hungry it is possible to get within a short time. Something in the air - and, of course, we're breathing filtered Europan air - speeds up normal digestion. We'll be starving to death in a couple of hours.'

'It seems to give you a sort of mournful satisfaction.' Thomas said dryly.

The young man flashed: T'm here to see that you don't get back alive to the settlement, that's all.'

Thomas scarcely heard him. His face was screwed into a black frown. 'The more you tell me, the more I am convinced that the human beings on Europa are a sorry lot, not true pioneers. They've been here fifty years, and they've built their cities with machines, and machine-operated their mines - and not a single individual has rooted himself in the soil. No one has learned to exist without the luxuries that were brought from Earth. You talk of their having slaved and created. Bah! I tell you, Ray Bartlett, this is a terrible indictment of these so-called pioneers of yours, who simply moved the equivalent of an Earth city here and live an artificial life, longing for the day, no doubt, when they're wealthy enough to get back to the real thing.'

The young man retorted grimly: 'Yes. Well, you try living off the soil of this barren moon - try killing a gryb with your bare hands.'

'Not my hands,' replied Thomas as grimly. 'My brains and my experience. We're going to get' back to the Five Cities in spite of these natural obstacles, in spite of you!'

In the silence that followed', Thomas examined their surroundings. He felt his first real chill of doubt as his eyes and mind took in that wild and desolate hell of rock that stretched to every horizon. No, not every! Barely visible in the remote distance of the direction they would have to go was a dark mist of black cliff.

It seemed to swim there against the haze of semi-blackness that was the sky beyond the horizon. In the near distance the piling rock showed fantastic shapes, as if frozen in a state of writhing anguish. And there was no beauty in it, no sweep of grandeur, simply endless, desperate miles of black, tortured deadness - and silence!

He grew aware of the silence with a start that pierced his body like a physical shock. The silence seemed suddenly alive. It pressed unrelentingly down upon that flat stretch of rock where they stood. A malevolent silence that kept on and on, without echoes, without even a wind now to whistle and moan over the billion caves and gouged trenches that honeycombed the bleak, dark, treacherous land around them. A silence that seemed the very spirit of this harsh and deadly little world, here under that tiny, cold, brilliant sun, little more than a dazzling, distorted point in the blue-black sky.

'Gets you, doesn't it?' Ray Bartlett said, and there was a sneer in his voice.

Thomas stared at him, without exactly seeing him. His gaze was far away.

'Yes,' he said thoughtfully. 'I'd forgotten what it felt like; and I hadn't realized how much I'd forgotten. Well, we'd better get started.'

As they leaped cautiously over the rock, assisted by the smaller gravitation of Europa, the young man said: 'Perhaps you'll understand better how we, who've built cities and homes on this far-away moon, feel about the prospect of being handed over to another government?'

'I am not,' said Thomas curtly, 'prepared to discuss the matter with a person who does not understand psychology, sociology, history and political economy. There is nothing more futile than arguing with someone who has no basis for his opinions but a vague backwash of emotions.'

'We know what's right and what's human,' Ray Bartlett replied icily. 'We've got our scientists, too, and our engineers and teachers; and I'm here to see that their decision to kill you is carried out.'

'You have only a knife now,' Thomas commented, 'and if you attacked me with that I'd have to show you the method employed by the Martian plainsmen to disarm a man with a knife. It's very simple, really, and consistently effective.'

'Yeah!' Ray Bartlett said roughly, his lean face tight, his formidable body tense. 'What good would that do? I could still tear you apart with my bare hands.'

Thomas slowed in his swift walking to glance at the other. 'I venture to suggest that, with my wide experience in my favour, you could do nothing against me. However,' he said hastily as the young man's dark eyes flashed with unfriendly intent, 'I apologize for making a provocative remark. My words might properly be construed as a dare -in fact, all threats, however veiled behind apparent reason and moral uplift, are dares - and history teaches that such provocation produces an inevitable physical conflict. Tell me, what do you do for a living?' 'I'm a metal engineer!' Ray Bartlett said gruffly. 'Oh,' Thomas's voice held a note of pleased surprise. 'I see that I've been underestimating you. No one will understand better than you the metal end of this business of Mars taking over Europa.'

'Mars isn't taking over Europa!' Bartlett snapped. 'And don't try to pull any flattery about how easy it should be for me to undertsand your subtle reasoning. I can see through that kind of stuff.'

Thomas ignored him. 'Here are the figures. The earth uses ten billion tons of steel every year; Mars two billion - ' 'That's proof,' Bartlett interjected, 'that they wouldn't dare go to war with us, because even as it is, we sell them half their steel. If we cut that out, they couldn't maintain their industries to supply peacetime needs, let alone wartime. We can tell them to go stick it.'

'You're quite wrong. Your reasoning is that of a newspaper correspondent who totals up the armaments of opposing sides and then says, "Look, we've got more!" War is the great unknown, the unpredictable. A military genius with a million men can lick a proportionately well-armed two million men. Up to a certain point, war is a science like astronomy, then it becomes astrology. So far as science can help us, our general staff has decided that, strategically, we are in a bad way. While we do not actually believe we would lose, we could not guarantee a victory.'

'That is the argument of conservative old women. They wouldn't dare to fight.'

'Here's the breakdown of figures,' Thomas went on calmly. 'Half our steel, as well as the billion tons we sell to Mars, is mined with great difficulty on Jupiter. We couldn't operate those mines in case of war because the mines are hopelessly vulnerable to attack. That leaves us five billion. We couldn't operate the mines on Titan, which provide a scant fifty million tons of steel, and, of course, Europa would be captured within a month of the war's beginning. The reason for all this is that it is militarily impossible for our ships to maintain the spacelanes between Earth and Jupiter, except at certain seasons of the year, when Mars was on the other side of the Sun from Jupiter. The Martians, however, would not start the war until the situation was favourable to them.

'Now, naturally, the Martians won't be able to operate the Jupiter mines under war conditions, but they should have no difficulty continuing operations on Ganymede, lo, Callisto, as well as Europa after they take it, and Titan, after they take that. Meantime, we'd have the supplies of Venus, the Moon and Earth, sufficient to supply us with some four billion tons a year. Considering the greater size of Earth, and the larger populations on Venus and Earth, they, with their smaller normally necessary needs, would actually have the advantage of us with their twelve hundred million tons.

'And all these mighty forces would be unleashed into a trillion-dollar war for what? To retain a paltry hundred million tons of steel - and other metals in proportion - from Europa. Naturally, we decided it wasn't worth it when we saw the way the political situation on Mars was tending towards one disastrous and inevitable end.'

'You damned cowards!' Ray Bartlett snarled. 'We're not fighting for steel. We're fighting to the last man and woman for our cities and our homes. Now, let's not talk about it any more. You make me sick with your cold, inhuman reasoning. Using human beings like pawns. Well, let me tell you, they're the only ones who count. Thank Heaven, you and I haven't a chance of getting out of this alive.'

Two hours later the Sun was high in those dark, gloomy heavens. It had been two hours of silence. Two hours while they tramped precariously along thin stretches of rock between fantastic valleys that yawned on either side, while they skirted the edges of caves whose bleak depths sheered straight down into the restless bowels of the moon. Two hours of desolation.

The great black cliff, no longer misted by distance, loomed near and gigantic. As far as the eye could see it stretched to either side; and from where Thomas toiled and leaped ever more wearily, its wall seemed to rear up abrupt and glassy and unscalable. He gasped:

'I didn't realize I was so out of condition. I hate to confess it, but I'm not sure I can climb that cliff.'

The young man turned a face towards him that had lost its brown healthiness in a grey, dull fatigue. A hint of fire came back into his dark eyes.

'It's hunger!' he said curtly. 'I told you what it would be like. We're starving.'

Thomas pressed on, but after a moment slackened his pace, and said: 'This grass eater - it also eats the smaller branches of trees, doesn't it?' 'Yes. That's what its long neck is for. What about it?' Ts that all it eats?' 'That and Jupiter grass!'

'Nothing else ?' Thomas's voice was sharp with question, his powerfully built face drawn tight with insistence. 'Think, man!' Ray Bartlett bridled. 'Don't take that tone to me. What's the use of all this, anyway?'

'Sorry - about the tone, I mean. What does it drink?'

'It licks ice. They always stay near the rivers. During the brief melting periods each year, all the water from the forests runs into the rivers and freezes. The only other thing it eats or drinks is salt. Like Earth animals, they absolutely have to have salt, and it's pretty rare.'

'Salt! That's it!' Thomas's voice was triumphant. 'We'll have to turn back. We passed a stretch of rock salt about a mile back. We'll have to get some.'

'Go back! Are you crazy?'

Thomas stared at him, his eyes grey pools of steely glitter. 'Listen Bartlett, I said a while ago that I didn't think I could climb those cliffs. Well, don't worry, I'll climb them. And I'll last through all today, and all tomorrow and the other twelve or fifteen or twenty days. I've put on about twenty-five pounds during the last ten years that I've been a cabinet minister. Well, dammit, my body'll use that as food, and by Heaven, I'll be alive and moving and going strong when you're staggering like a drunken sailor. I'll be alive when you're dead and buried for a hundred miles. But if we expect to kill a grass eater and live decently, we've got to have salt. I saw some salt, and we can't take a chance on passing it up. So back we go.'

They glared at each other with the wild, tempestuous anger of two men whose nerves are on ultimate edge. Then Bartlett drew a deep breath and said:

'I don't know what your plan is, but it sounds crazy to me. Have you ever seen a grass eater ? Well, it looks something like a giraffe, only it's bigger, and faster on its feet. Maybe you've got some idea of tempting it with salt, and then killing it with a knife. I tell you, you can't get near it - But I'll go back with you. It doesn't matter, because we're going to die, no matter what you think. What I'm hoping is that a gryb sees us. It'll be quick that way.'

'There is something,' said Thomas, 'pitiful and horrible about a young man who is determined to die.'

'You don't think I want to die!' the young man flashed. 'Why, I had everything to live for, until you came along with your miserable - '

His passionate voice died abruptly, but Thomas knew better than to let so much fierce feeling die unexplored.

'No doubt,' he ventured softly, 'there is a girl you love -'

He saw by the wretched look on the young man's face that he had struck home.

'Ah, well' said Thomas, 'she'll probably marry someone else. There's always a second man who desires to taste of the manifold delights and charms of a beautiful and intelligent girl'

The young man said nothing; and Thomas realized his words had started a cruel train of thought in the other. He felt no compunction. It was absolutely imperative that Ray Bartlett develop a desire to live. In the crisis that seemed all too near now, his assistance might easily be the difference between life and death.

It was odd, the fever of talk that came upon Thomas as they laboriously retraced their steps to the salt rock. It was as if his tongue, of all his body, had become intoxicated; and yet his words, though swift, were not incoherent, but reasoned and calculated to convince the younger man:

'Look at it this way. Your people, over a period of fifty years, have built five cities, with a total population of a million. You produce from your mines a hundred million tons of steel, a thousand tons of platinum, and about a hundred million tons of other metals - about two hundred million tons altogether. Of course, that's per year.

'Now, your engineers pointed out that estimates of Europa's recoverable metals indicated that in a thousand years the supply will be exhausted. In other words, there are two hundred billion tons of metal on this little moon, equal to twenty years of the normal needs of Earth. The value of the entire thousand years' supply, at an average of twenty dollars per ton, is four thousand billion dollars. I need hardly tell you that a war between Earth and Mars would cost ten times that much for each year that it lasted, not counting the hundred to two hundred million lives that would be destroyed in every conceivable horrible manner, the brutalizing of minds that would take place, the destruction of liberty that would ensue. Did the leaders of your community consider that in their deliberations?'

'I tell you,' Ray Bartlett contended stubbornly, 'the Martians won't fight, if you stand up to them and - '

'You keep repeating that like a parrot!' Thomas snapped.

'The internal political situation on Mars has reached an explosive point. There are two groups on the planet - one ferociously hostile to Earth, the other - the government -believing in negotiation. We want that government to stay in power, but they haven't a chance in the elections this year unless they can show material progress. Europa will be their answer - '

'Here's your salt!' Bartlett interrupted him curtly.

The salt rock composed a narrow ledge that protruded like a long fence which ran along in a startlingly straight line and ended abruptly at a canyon's edge, the fence rearing up, as if cringing back in frank dismay at finding itself teetering on the brink of an abyss.

Thomas picked up two pieces of salt rubble and slipped them into the capacious pockets of his plainsmanlike coat -and started back towards the dark wall of cliff nearly three miles away. He took up the thread of his argument where he had left off:

'And remember this. It's not only Europa's recoverable metals that will be used up in a thousand years, but also the metal resources of the entire Solar System. That's why we must have an equitable distribution now, because we can't afford to spend the last hundred of those thousand years fighting over metal with Mars. You see, in that thousand years we must reach the stars. We must develop speeds immeasurably greater than that of light - and in that last, urgent, hundred years we must have their co-operation, not their enmity. Therefore they must not be dependent on us for anything; and we must not be under the continual mind-destroying temptation of being able to save ourselves for a few years longer if we sacrifice them.'

Ray Bartlett said, rage nearly choking his voice: 'I can see what you're trying to do - pretending that you're capable of thinking of the long-run welfare of the world. Well, forget it; you're not God. People get to believe they are, you know; and that they can so manipulate the strings of their puppet ideas and puppet men that everything will inevitably happen as they desire. But we're not puppets, we human beings. In a thousand years, anything can happen.'

He finished roughly: 'And now I tell you again to shut up! I don't want to hear your arguments. You said before that the basis of our beliefs is different. You're damned right it is. So shut up, damn you! I'm so hungry that I can hardly stand up.'

'Well,' Thomas asked wearily, 'what is the basis of your opinions? I am willing to .debate on your basis.'

The young man made no answer. They trudged along in silence.

Thomas's body ached in every muscle and every nerve pulsed alarms to his brain. He clung with a desperate, stubborn strength to each bit of rock projecting from the cliff wall, horribly aware that a slip meant death. Once he looked down, and his brain reeled in black dismay from the fearful depths that fell away behind him.

Through blurred vision he saw the young man a few feet away, the tortured lines of his face a grim reminder of the hunger weakness that was corroding the very roots of their two precariously held lives.

'Hang on!' Thomas gasped. 'It's only a few more yards.'

They made it, and collapsed on the very edge of that terrific chasm of cliff, too weary to climb the gentle slope that remained before they could look over the country beyond, too exhausted to do anything but lie there, sucking the life-giving air into their lungs. At last Ray Bartlett gasped:

'What's the use? If we had any sense we'd jump off this cliff and get it over with.'

'We can jump into a deep cave any time,' Thomas retorted. 'Let's get going.'

He rose shakily to his feet, took a few steps, then stiffened and flung himself down with a hissing intake of his breath. His fingers grabbed the other's leg and jerked him back brutally to a prone position:

'Down for your life. There's a herd of grass eaters half a mile away. And they mean life for us.'

Bartlett crawled up beside him, almost eagerly; and the two peered cautiously over the knob of rock out into a grassy plain. The plain was somewhat below them, Thomas saw. To the left, a scant hundred yards away, like a wedge driven into the grassland, was the pointed edge of a forest. The grass beyond seemed almost like a projection of the forest growth. It, too, formed a wedge that petered out in bleak rock. At the far end of the grass was a herd of about half a hundred grass eaters.

'They're working this way!' Thomas said. 'And they'll pass close to that wedge of trees.'

A faint fire of irony edged Bartlett's voice as he said: 'And what will you do - run out and put salt on their tails? I tell you, Thomas, we haven't got a thing that - '

'Our first course,' said Thomas, unheeding, seeming to think out loud, 'is to get into that thick belt of trees. We can do that by skirting along this cliff's edge, and putting the trees between us and the animals. Then you can loan me your knife.'

'OK!' the young man agreed in a tired voice. 'If you won't listen, you'll have to learn from experience. I tell you, you won't get within a quarter of a mile of those things.'

'I don't want to,' Thomas replied. 'You see, Bartlett, if you had more confidence in life, you'd realize that this problem of killing animals by cunning has been solved before. It's absolutely amazing how similarly it has been solved on different worlds, and under widely differing conditions. One would almost suspect a common evolution, but actually it is only a parallel situation producing a parallel solution. Just watch me.'

'I'm willing,' said Ray Bartlett. 'There's almost any way I'd rather die than by starving. A meal of cooked grass eater is tough going, but it'll be pure heaven. Don't forget, though, that the bloodsucker grybs follow grass-eater herds, get as near as possible at night, then kill them in the morning when they're frozen. Right now, with darkness near, a gryb must be out there somewhere, hiding, sneaking nearer. Pretty soon he'll smell us, and then he'll - '

'We'll come to the gryb when he comes for us!' said Thomas calmly. 'I'm sorry I never visited this moon in my younger days; these problems would all have been settled long ago. In the meantime, the forest is our goal.'

Thomas's outward calmness was but a mask for his inner excitement. His body literally shook with hunger and desire as they reached the safety of the forest. His fingers were trembling violently as he took Bartlett's knife and began to dig at the base of a great, bare, brown tree. 'It's the root, isn't it,' he asked unsteadily, 'that's so tough and springy that it's almost like fine tempered steel, and won't break even if it's bent into a circle? They call it eurood on Earth, and it's used in industry.'

'Uh-huh,' Bartlett agreed. 'What are you going to do -make a bow? I suppose you could use a couple of grass blades in place of catgut. The grass is pretty strong and makes good rope.'

'No,' said Thomas. 'I'm not making a bow and arrow. Mind you, I can shoot a pretty mean arrow. But I'm remembering what you said about not being able to get within a quarter of a mile of the beasts.'

He jerked out a root, which was about an inch in thickness, cut off a generous two-foot length, and began to sharpen, first one end, then the other.

It was hard going, harder than he had expected, because the knife skidded along the surface as if it was so much metal. Finally it obtained a cutting hold. 'Makes a good edge and point,' he commented. 'And now, give me a hand in bending this double, while I tie some grass blades around to keep it that way.'

'O-oh!' said Bartlett wonderingly. 'I see-e-e! Say, that is clever. It'll make a mouthful about six inches in diameter. The grass eater that gets it will gobble it up in one gulp to prevent any of the others getting the salt you're going to smear on it. His digestive juices will dissolve the grass string, the points will spring apart and tear the wall of his stomach, producing an internal haemorrhage.'

'It's a method,' said Thomas, 'used by the primitives of Venus to kill the elusive Paamer deer; the Martian plainsman kills the water gopher with it, and, last but not least, our own Eskimo back on Earth uses it on wolves. Naturally, they all use different kinds of bait, but the principle is the same.'

He made his way cautiously to the edge of the forest. From the shelter of a tree he flung the little piece of bent wood with all his strength. It landed in the grass a hundred and fifty feet away.

'We'd better make some more!' Thomas said. 'We can't depend on one being found.'

The eating was good; the cooked meat tough but tasty; and it was good, too, to feel the flow of strength into his body.

Thomas sighed at last and stood up, glanced at the sinking Sun, an orange-sized ball of flame in the western sky.

'We'll have to carry sixty Earth pounds of meat apiece; that's four pounds a day for the next fifteen days. Eating meat alone is dangerous; we may go insane, though it really requires about a month for that. We've got to carry the meat because we can't waste any more time killing grass eaters.'

Thomas began to cut into the meaty part of the animal, which lay stretched out on the tough grass; and in a few minutes had tied together two light bundles. By braiding grass together, he made himself a pack sack and lifted the long shank of meat until it was strapped to his back. There was a little adjustment necessary to keep the weight from pressing his electrically heated clothes too tightly against him; when he looked up finally, he saw that the young man was looking at him peculiarly.

'You realize, of course,' Bartlett said, 'that you're quite insane now. It's true that, with these heated suits, we may be able to live through the cold of tonight, provided we find a deep cave. But don't think for a second that, once a gryb gets on our trail, we'll be able to throw it a piece of sharpened wood and expect it to have an internal haemorrhage.'

'Why not?' Thomas asked; and his voice was sharp.

'Because it's the toughest creature ever spawned by a crazy evolution, the main reason I imagine why no intelligent form of life evolved on Europa. Its claws are literally diamond hard; its teeth can twist metals out of shape; its stomach wall can scarcely be cut with a knife, let alone a crudely pointed wood.'

His voice took on a harsh note of exasperation: 'I'm glad we've had this meal; starving wasn't my idea of a pleasant death. I want the quick death that the gryb will give us. But for Heaven's sake, get it out of your head that we shall live through this. I tell you, the monster will follow us into any cave, cleverly enlarge it wherever he has difficulty; and he'll get us because eventually we'll reach a dead end. They're not normal caves, you know, but meteor holes, the result of a cosmic cataclysm millions of years ago, and they're all twisted out of shape by the movement of the planet's crust. As for tonight, we'd better get busy and find a deep cave with plenty of twists in it, and perhaps a place where we can block the air currents from coming in. The winds will be arriving about a half-hour before the sun goes down, and our electric heaters won't be worth anything against those freezing blasts. It might pay us to gather some of the dead wood lying around, so we can build a fire at the really cold part of the night.'

Getting the wood into the cave was simple enough. They gathered great armfuls of it, and tossed it down to where it formed a cluttering pile at the first twist in the tunnel. Then, having gathered all the loose wood in the vicinity, they lowered themselves down to the first level, Thomas first in a gingerly fashion; the young man - Thomas noticed - with a snap and spring. A smile crinkled the lips of the older man. The spirit of youth, he reflected, would not be suppressed.

They were just finishing throwing the wood down to the next level when suddenly a shadow darkened the cave mouth. Thomas glanced up with a terrible start and had a fleeting glimpse of great fanged jaws and glowing eyes that glared from a hideous head; a thick red tongue licked out in unholy desire, and a spray of saliva rained down upon their transparent metal helmets and leather-like clothes. And then Ray Bartlett's leather-covered hands bit like sharp stones into Thomas's arm; he felt himself dragged over the edge.

They landed unhurt among the loose pile of branches below; and scrambled frantically to throw it farther down. A great mad clawing and horrible bass mewing above them whipped them to desperate speed. They made it, as that enormous head peered down from the second level, visible only by the phosphorescent glow of its eyes, like two burning coals a foot and a half apart.

There was a terrific scrambling sound behind the two men as they pushed wildly down to the next level; a rock bounced down, narrowly missing them as it clattered past; and then, abruptly, silence and continuing darkness.

'What happened?' Thomas asked in bewilderment.

There was bitterness in Ray Bartlett's voice as he replied: 'It's wedged itself in, because it's realized it can't get us in the few minutes left before it freezes for the night; and, of course, now we won't be able to get out past it, with that great body squeezed against the rock sides.

'It's really a very clever animal in its way. It never chases grass eaters, but just follows them. It has discovered that it wakes up a few minutes before they do; naturally, it thinks we, too, will freeze, and that it will wake up before we will. In any event, it knows we can't get out. And we can't. We're finished.'

All that long night, Thomas waited and watched. There were times when he dozed, and there were times when he thought he was dozing, only to realize with a dreadful start that the horrible darkness had played devil's tricks on his mind.

The darkness during the early part of the night was like a weight that held them down. Not the faintest glimmer of natural light penetrated that Stygian night. And when, at last, they made a fire from their pile of brush, the pale, flickering flames pushed but feebly against the pressing, relentless force of the darkness and seemed helpless against the cold.

Thomas began to notice the cold, first as an uncomfortable chill that ate into his flesh, and then as a steady, almost painful, clamminess that struck into his very bones. The cold was noticeable, too, in the way white hoar-frost thickened on the walls. Great cracks appeared in the rock; and not once, but several times, sections of the ceiling collapsed with a roar that threatened their lives. The first clatter of falling debris seemed to waken Bartlett from a state of semi-coma. He jerked to his feet; and Thomas watched him silently as he paced restlessly to and fro, clapping his gloved, heated hands together to keep them warm.

'Why not,' Thomas asked, 'go up and build a fire against the gryb's body ? If we burn him - '

'He'd just wake up,' Bartlett said tersely, 'and besides, his hide won't burn at ordinary temperatures. It has all the properties of metallic asbestos, conducts heat, but is practically noncombustible.'

Thomas was silent, frowning; then: 'The toughness of this creature is no joke - and the worst of it all is that our danger, the whole affair, has been utterly useless. Fake handwriting or not, my colleagues will know the truth and will suspect foul play. Rumours to that effect will spread automatically through the press and develop into open vilification of the murderous Five Cities. Before you know it, there will be a swelling murmur of demand for retribution; and m such a dark atmosphere it will be the simplest matter in the world to hand Europa over to Mars. You think that's far-fetched, don't you?'

'It's crazy!' half whispered Ray Bartlett shakily.

'You may not realize it even now,' Thomas went on, 'but the person to have concentrated upon was myself. I don't think I am exaggerating when I say that any solution which I proposed would have been accepted. My reputation has been the conduct of a peculiar set of circumstances, but, once established, it acquired rocklike qualities. The report of my death will create a sensation and have all the effects that I have described.'

'Well, what should we have done ?' Ray Bartlett exclaimed with dark bitterness. 'We showed you all our resources because we were determined to leave you no excuse. But what could we do against a person who thought in billions where we thought in millions? To you everything was small, unimportant. The full capacity of all our mines was just a drop in the tremendous maw of Earth's metal furnaces. What could we do ?'

'Accept the situation!' Thomas shrugged. 'What's the difference whether you sold your metal hereafter to Mars or to Earth; all you ever see are the big freight ships that come here and load up; there would be no objection to making a stipulation that the community have submitted to them the names of governors that Mars would place here, from which they could take their choice. We could also stipulate that the Martians live in separate cities to begin with, and that all business relations between individuals be on a purely voluntary basis; and, oh, a hundred other stipulations could be made, to be effective during, say, the first fifty years.'

'I don't really suppose it matters,' the young man said gloomily. 'I suppose we are stupid fools to object to being handed over like a herd of sheep. It's our pride, and, in a kind of way, I can see your point about the unfairness of the distribution of natural resources. Oh, Lord, here am I talking again. What's the use of you and I arguing on this subject? It's too late. In a few hours that damn thing that's got us sealed in here will wake up and finish us. There's nothing we've got that can hold it back one inch, or one second.'

'Don't be so sure of that!' Thomas said. '! admit the toughness of this monster has got me worried sick, but don't forget what I've said: These problems have been solved before on other planets.'

'You're mad! I tell you, sir, even with an atomic gun it's touch and go getting the gryb before it gets you. Its hide is so tough it won't begin to disintegrate until your heart's in your boots. What can we do against a thing like that when all we've got is a knife ?'

'Let me have the knife,' Thomas replied. 'I want to sharpen it.'

His face twisted into a wry smile. Perhaps it didn't mean much, but the young man had called him 'sir' quite unconsciously. There were psychological implications in the use of the word.

The sustained darkness of that night, the insistent crackle of the palely flickering fire seemed to become more and more alive as the nervous hours twitched by. It was Thomas who was pacing now, his medium-tall, powerful body restless and tense With anxious uncertainty.

It was getting distinctly warmer; the white hoar-frost was melting in places, yielding for the first time to the heat of the spluttering flames; and the chill was no longer reaching clammily through his heated clothes.

A scatter of fine ashes lay on the ground, indication of how completely the fuel had burned away; but even as it was the cave was beginning to show a haze of smoke fumes, through which it was difficult to see properly.

Abruptly there was a great stirring above them; and then a deep, eager mewing, and a scrambling, scratching sound. Ray Bartlett jerked erect from where he had been lying and leaped to his feet. He gasped:

'It's awake, and it's remembered.'

'Well,' said Thomas grimly, 'this is what you've been longing for.'

From across the fire the young man stared at him moodily. He said harshly: 'You don't think I want to die, do you? Besides, I'm beginning to see that killing you will solve nothing. It was a mad scheme.'

'You agree, then,' said Thomas, 'that people who have not rooted themselves into a land, but are simply exploiting it, have no right to expect the living, vital organism of the people to which they belong, to risk a death blow in order to protect them and their purely artificial structure ?'

'Oh, I don't know what I think!' Ray Bartlett exclaimed. 'For Heaven's sake, let's quit quibbling. That damned thing-'

A rock bounded down and crashed between them, missing the fire, then vanishing noisily into the darkness beyond. There followed a horrible squeezing, a rasping sound as of brittle scales scraping rock; and then, terribly near, the drumming sound as of a monstrous sledgehammer at work.

'He's breaking off a piece of rock!' Bartlett panted. 'Quick! Get into a concavity against the wall. Those rocks may come tumbling down here, and they won't miss us forever - What are you doing ?'

'I'm afraid,' said Thomas in a shaky voice, 'I've got to risk the rock. There's no time to waste.'

His leather-covered hands trembled with the excitement that gripped him as he hastily unfastened one of the glove extensions. He winced a little as his hand emerged into the open air, and immediately jerked it over the hot flame of the fire.

'Phew, it's cold. Must still be about ninety below. I'll have to warm this knife or it'll stick to my skin.'

He held the blade into the flame, finally withdrew it, made a neat incision in the thumb of his bare hand, and wiped the blood on to the knife blade, smearing it on until his hand, blue with the cold, refused to bleed any more. Then he quickly slipped it back into its glove.

It tingled as it warmed, but in spite of the pain he picked up a flaming faggot by its unburned end and walked along into the darkness, his eyes searching the floor. He was vaguely aware of the young man following him.

'Ah,' Thomas said, and even in his own ears his voice sounded wrenched from him. He knelt quiveringly beside a thin crack in the rock. 'This'll be just about right. It's practically against the wall, protected from falling rocks by this projecting edge of wall.'

He glanced up at Bartlett. 'The reason I had us camp here last night instead of farther down was because this ledge is nearly sixty feet long. The gryb is about thirty feet long from tail to snout, isn't it?'

'Yes!'

'Well, this will give it room to come down and walk a few feet; and besides, the cave is wide enough here for us to squeeze past it when it's dead.'

'When it's dead!' the young man echoed with a groan. 'You must be the world's prize fool - '

Thomas scarcely heard him. He was carefully inserting the handle of the knife into the crack of the rock, wedging it in. He tested it.

'Hm-m-m, it seems solid enough. But we'll have to make doubly sure.'

'Hurry!' Bartlett exclaimed. 'We've got to get down to the next level. There's just a chance that there is a connection somewhere below with another cave.'

'There isn't! I went down to investigate while you were sleeping. There are only two more levels after this.'

'For Heaven's sake, man, it'll be here in a minute.'

'A minute is all I need!' Thomas replied, struggling to calm his clamouring heart, to slow the convulsive gasping of his lungs. 'I want to pound these slivers of rock beside the knife to brace it.'

And Thomas pounded, while Bartlett danced frantically from one foot to another in a perfect panic of anxiety. He pounded while that scrambling from above became a roaring confusion, so near now that it was deafening. He pounded while his nerves jangled and shook from the hellish bass mewing that blasted down from the ravenous beast.

And then, with a gasp, he flung aside the piece of rock with which he had been hammering; and the two men lowered themselves recklessly over the ledge - just as two great glowing eyes peered down upon them.

The firelight revealed the vague outlines of a dark, fanged mouth, a thick, twisting tongue; and then there was a scaly glitter as the monstrosity plunged downward right on to the fire.

Thomas saw no more. He let go his hold and skittered downward for nearly twenty feet before he struck bottom. For a minute he lay there, too dizzy to realize that the scrambling noise from above had stopped.

Instead there was a low grunting of pain, and then a sucking sound.

'What the dickens!' Ray Bartlett muttered.

'Wait!' Thomas whispered tensely.

They waited what must have been five minutes, then ten - half an hour. The sucking sound above was weaker. An overtone of wheezing accompanied it, and the grunts had stopped. Once there was a low, hoarse moan of agony.

'Help me up!' Thomas whispered. 'I want to see how close it is to death.'

'Listen,' snapped Ray Bartlett, 'either you're mad or I'm going to be. For Heaven's sake, what's it doing ?'

'It smelled the blood on the knife,' Thomas replied, 'and began to lick it. The licking cut its tongue into ribbons, which whipped it into a frenzy, because with every lick more of its own blood would flow into its mouth. You say it loves blood. For the last half-hour it's been gorging itself on its own blood. Primitive stuff, common to all the planets. Givilized men, apparently, never think of things like that.'

'I guess,' Ray Bartlett said in a queer voice after a long moment, 'there's nothing now to prevent us getting back to the Five Cities.'

Thomas stared with narrowed eyes at the other's vague bulk in the darkness. 'Nothing, except - you!'

They climbed in silence to where the gryb lay dead. Thomas was aware of Barltett watching him as he gingerly removed the knife from where it was wedged into the rock. Then abruptly, harshly, Bartlett said:

'Give me that!'

Thomas hesitated, then handed the knife over. It was possible he would have to take the terrific risk of telling young Bartlett the truth about this whole business. For undoubtedly the younger man was once again all enemy.

Outside, the morning greeted them, bleak, yet somehow more inviting. The little red Sun was well above the horizon, and something else was in the sky, too: a huge red ball of pale fire, Jupiter the giant sinking now towards the western horizon.

The sky, the world of Europa, was lighter, brighter; even the rocks didn't look so dead, nor so black. A strong wind was blowing; and it added to the sense of life. The morning seemed cheerful after the black night, as if hope was once again possible.

'It's a false hope,' thought Thomas. 'The Lord save me from the stubborn duty sense of an honest man. He's going to attack.'

Yet the fury of attack, when it came, surpassed his expectations. He caught the movement, the flash of the knife out of the corner of his eye - and whipped aside.

The knife caught the resisting fabric of the arm of his electrically heated suit, scraped a foot-long scar on that obstinate, half-metallic substance, and then Thomas was dancing away along a ledge of firm rock.

'You silly fool!' he gasped. 'You don't know what you're doing.'

'You bet I know!' Bartlett ground out 'I've got orders to kill you, and I'm going to in spite of your silver tongue. You're the devil himself for talking, but now you die.'

He leaped forward, knife poised, and Thomas let him come. There was a way of disarming a man with a knife, provided the man did not know the method and provided it worked the first time.

Bartlett grunted as he leaped; his free hand grabbed at Thomas, and that was all Thomas needed. Just a damned amateur who didn't know knife fighters didn't try for holds.

Thomas snatched at the clawlike spread of that striking hand, caught it with grim strength and jerked the young man past him with every ounce of his power. As Bartlett shot by him, propelled by his own momentum as well as by that arm-wrenching pull, Thomas twisted along with him. At the last instant he braced himself for the shock and sent the two-hundred-pound body spinning along like a top.

Frantically, Ray Bartlett fought for balance. But there was no mercy in that rough ground. Upjutting rock snagged his feet; he fell with mind-stunning violence, kicked weakly and lay still.

Thomas picked up the knife from where it had fallen.

'I'll keep this,' he said when the other's glazed eyes began to show animation. 'But what am I going to do with you? We've got twelve days, at least, during which I'll be at your mercy a score of times a day. A swiftly heaved rock to smash my head, a sudden shove as we skirt some crater - '

Til do it too.'

Thomas frowned. 'At least, you're honest. That makes it possible for me not to kill you, but to trust you with a secret so important that if the barest hint of it got out in advance it would shatter the greatest diplomatic stroke of the ages. But I must have your most sacred word of honour that not one word will escape you under any circumstances.' 'I guess I can promise that!' Ray Bartlett said in a thick, unsteady voice; then, with more fire: 'But I'll see you in hell before I change my mind.' 'You promise, nevertheless.' 'Yes, I promise, but there's nothing -'

Thomas cut him short: 'There has never been a more enlightened group of men on Mars than the present government. If we hand over Europa to prove our good will to the doubters among the opposition, that government will, immediately on re-election, vote to join the Earth-Venus union. I need hardly tell you that the thing is so tremendous that it staggers the imagination. For the first time in the history of men - '

'Suppose they lose the election?'

'We can trust that crew of rabble-rousers to encroach immediately on the rights of the Europans, as defined by the agreement we will draw up. Whereupon we shall declare the agreement null and void and take over Europa.'

'Bah! That means war, and you wouldn't have the nerve.'

Thomas's steely eyes gazed unflinchingly at the younger man. 'Let me tell you that I am the dominating minister in the present Earth-Venus government; and I hope I have convinced you that fear is not one of my characteristics. My colleagues and I,do not fear, but hate, war. However, we are convinced that war will not be necessary. The government on Mars will win the election; and I think that you agree with me there.'

Bartlett muttered: 'Getting Europa handed to them on a platter ought to swing any election, I guess.'

Thomas ignored his surliness, and in a voice that was queerly husky he said: 'I have talked of repetition being a rule of life. But somewhere along the pathway of the Universe there must be a first time for everything, a first peaceful solution along sound sociological lines of the antagonisms of great sovereign powers.

'Some day man will reach the stars, and all the old, old problems will repeat themselves. When that day comes, we must have established sanity in the very souls of men, so firmly rooted that there will be an endless repetition of peaceful solutions.'

He stood up. 'Think it over, and then decide for yourself whether you've got the nerve to face the recriminations of your friends for letting me come in alive. There's a dark, bitter period ahead of Europa, and the agony of your people will be heaped on your head. It's a hard choice.'

In the west, mighty Jupiter was being engulfed by the blue, dark horizon, an age-old cycle repeating. The strong wind died, and there was quiet upon that wild, fantastic land. Thomas was aware of the young man walking behind him -too aware; it made him less alert for what was ahead.

Abruptly he stumbled to the edge of a jagged black hole that fell away into sheer, dreadful depths. He hung there, teetering, frantic, over the abyss.

And then two iron-hard hands caught his shoulder, jerked him back from that desperate danger.

'Be careful, sir!' breathed the anxious voice of Ray Bartlett. 'Be careful, or you'll be killed.'